<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lachrimæ: or lamentations over the dead wherin is described the earnest zeale of the godly, in mourning for the sins of the people, who are dead in trespasses and sinnes. By Nathanael Cannon, minister and preacher of the word at Hurley, in Berkshire.</title>
            <author>Cannon, Nathanael, 1581 or 2-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848625</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17916)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 642:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lachrimæ: or lamentations over the dead wherin is described the earnest zeale of the godly, in mourning for the sins of the people, who are dead in trespasses and sinnes. By Nathanael Cannon, minister and preacher of the word at Hurley, in Berkshire.</title>
                  <author>Cannon, Nathanael, 1581 or 2-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 57+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for William Welby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In three parts: part 1 is "Lacrimæ"; part 2 is "A day of hearing, granted to Sion"; part 3 is "The spring garden or nurserie of spirituall plants".</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; part 1 only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13734:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LACHRIMAE: OR LAMENTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS OVER THE DEAD, WHERIN is deſcribed the earneſt zeale <hi>of the godly, in mourning for</hi> the ſins of the people, who are dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Cannon,</hi> Miniſter and Preacher of the Word at <hi>Hurley, in Berkshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZECH. 9.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Set a marke vpon the foreheads of thoſe men that mourne for the abominations that are done in the City.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IEREMY 9.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O that my head were a well of water, and my eyes a fountaine of teares, to lament the ſinnes of the people.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>William Welby.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13734:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13734:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS AND WORTHIE Lady, the Lady <hi>Milwarde,</hi> wife to <hi>the Right Worſhipfull, Sir</hi> RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT MILVVARD Knight, <hi>N. C.</hi> wiſheth the bleſſings of this life, and the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F externall actions may any way witneſſe our internall affections; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verily I haue like a Herald, fitly placed your Ladyſhip amongst the chiefe mourners; euen amongst thoſe whoſe hearts bleed, and whoſe eyes guſh out with riuers of teares, to ſee the abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theſe our latter and worſer daies.</p>
            <p>Chriſt wept ouer Hieruſalem, and often would hee haue gathered her together as a
<pb facs="tcp:13734:3"/>hen doth her chickins, but ſhee would not: Matth. <hi>23.37.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good Christians do the like, they mourne and melt into teares, to heare, to ſee, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, how God is prouoked, his holy name blaſphemed, his word neglected, his Sacraments contemned.</p>
            <p>O how ſinne raigneth, how the diuell ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth! neuer was the ſoule of iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> more vexed amongst the Sodomites, then are the conſciences of Gods children grieued to ſee <hi>Demas</hi> forſake God to follow the world; to heare the blaſphemies of <hi>Rabſaketh;</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the little faith and truth amongst the ſonnes of men; to marke the open wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſecret practiſes, the lacke of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the height of hypocriſie, when men doe ſinne, and thinke they are not ſeene.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like enormities doe cauſe the holy ones of Iſrael to open their ſpiritual ſluces, and to empty themſelues in prayers and teares, in grones and lamentations for the ſinnes of the people.</p>
            <p>In which number (vertuous Lady) I haue been bould to reckon you, and for
<pb facs="tcp:13734:3"/>ſuch a Principall, as that I cannot ſay who may haue more right vnto mourning weeds then your ſelfe in this kind.</p>
            <p>For mine owne particular, it may grow queſtionable, vpon what acquaintance I haue offered this poore treatiſe to your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that in this I am vpon a good ground; for the fruits of your religion hath led me forward, and I am ready to iuſtifie this commendation. We haue met together often in the houſe of God, where I alwaies noted you feruent in prayer, and diligent in hearing.</p>
            <p>You haue with your worthie Knight al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo giuen teſtimonie of your loue vnto Gods Miniſters; and in particular, vnto vs who were the Lecturers of the place, where you ſometimes make your abode.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing this was deliuered by me in that place, and that it was for the good of others to ſee the light, I knew no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons ſo fit in that Auditorie, as your ſelfe to ſend it vnto.</p>
            <p>Vouchſafe therefore (good Madam)
<pb facs="tcp:13734:4"/>to take notice of it, and let it haue place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst thoſe tokens of good will, that the world hath cauſe to preſent vnto you.</p>
            <p>Whileſt I betake my ſelfe to prayer for you and yours, with al the reſt of your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian familie; whom with your ſelfe I now recommend vnto the throne of Grace, with a deſire to be eſteemed,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladyſhips in all dutie,</hi> Nathanael Cannon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13734:4"/>
            <head>LACHRIMAE: <hi>OR</hi> LAMENTATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS OVER THE DEAD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 119. VERS. 136.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>My eyes guſh out with Riuers of waters, becauſe men keepe not thy law.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Theſe Canticles (for ſo a man may fitly call the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided parts of this Pſal.) being conſidered in the whole, doe properly, and very liuely preſent vnto vs the ſtate and condition of the Regenerate man: For looke what good affections and motions are to be found in a man newly begotten
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13734:5"/>to the Lord, the ſame ſhall wee haue collected in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of this Pſalme. Whether it bee Conſolation for the fruition of the ſpirit, or recuperation after the abſence of the Lord for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: or confirmation, which ſeales vp mercy to our ſoules: or correction, which brings vs home to the Lord: or reſolution, which challengeth any thing that would ſeparate vs from Chriſt Ieſus: or ſpirituall paſſion in a caſe of conſcience: or lamentation to behold the ſins of the people. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, I ſay, may ſerue to deſcribe the new man who is both ſanctified and mortified, this Pſalme will preſent it.</p>
            <p>In this Pſalme three things are of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall note: Firſt, the Title. Secondly, the Author. Thirdly, the Matter.</p>
            <p>The Title of this Pſalme is of an high ſtraine. <hi>Huic Pſalmo Titulus praeponitur: (Alta): Quia factus est ad laudandum Deum:</hi> as the learned obſerue.</p>
            <p>The author of this Pſalme was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> as <hi>Ierome, Ambroſe, Origen,</hi> &amp; other
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13734:5"/>of the Fathers affirme. For it was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him out of his particular occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as from a very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fluence of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which ſtill cald vpon to call vpon God.</p>
            <p>The Matter of this Pſalme hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers obſeruations, but eſpecially foure, that no other Pſalme in the whole booke hath beſides.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Dauid</hi> is alwaies preſented vnto vs in this Pſalme, ſpeaking as it were with God himſelfe without digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His petitions are altogether ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall in this Pſalme, and not for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall cauſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is deſcribed by the order of the Hebrew Alphabet, there being ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts, and euery part entitled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe ſeuerall characters.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That there is not one verſe in that Pſalme, amongſt the whole 176. verſes, but the Law of God is repeated in it, although it be <hi>per diuerſa vocabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la:</hi> either <hi>verbum Dei,</hi> or <hi>lex Dei,</hi> or <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicia
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13734:6"/>dei,</hi> or <hi>teſtimonia Dei:</hi> in euery one of them either the law of God, or the word of God, or the iudgement of God, or the teſtimonies of God.</p>
            <p>The Phraſe that my text expreſſeth, is the law of God, and the affection, or ſpiritual paſſion, that our Princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet will herein diſcouer, is a caſe of teares, moſt abundantly ſhead, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the Trope or figure heere vſed, Whole riuers of teares, as it were a very floud to drowne ſinne in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge thereof.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtands forth as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent patterne of piety, whoſe heart doth lanch forth into a maine Ocean, &amp; cannot endure that his God ſhould bee openly prouoked: zeale hath ſo wrought vpon him in this caſe, that he is euen conſumed therewith, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſeth in the 139. verſe of this Pſalme.</p>
            <p>The parts that wee are generally to conſider in the diſtribution of this text, are two:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13734:6"/>
               <hi>Diuiſion,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A <hi>Lamentation,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>My eyes guſh out with riuers of waters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A <hi>Reaſon</hi> of this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>becauſe men keepe not thy law.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Out of the <hi>Lamentation,</hi> I obſerue his zeale. It pierceth his heart, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth through his reines, which makes him weepe bitterly, and ſo abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that whole riuers of teares are ſaid to ſtreame from him.</p>
            <p>Out of the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I obſerue the true ground of his zeale, it is in Gods cauſe; it is not a fantaſticall paſſion, as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times amongſt carnall men, who are often dround in teares for worldly loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; or elſe haue tickling affections for earthly delights: but this is ſound and ſubſtantiall for Gods glory. It is with the heart of Gods child, as it was with the Altar of the Lord, Leuit. 6.13.</p>
            <p>That Altar muſt neuer be without fier, no more muſt the heart of Gods child bee without burning affections
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13734:7"/>for Gods glory, but ſtill the ſparkles muſt flie vpwards, and ſtill the heart muſt be on fire, either reioycing in that God is praiſed, or elſe lamenting when God is diſhonoured: from whence we are taught a moſt excellent and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Whoſoeuer hath Gods ſpirit, muſt be zealous for Gods glory. It was a great reproch vnto the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Reuel. 3. verſ. 1. in that ſhee had a name to liue, and yet was dead, dead in ſenſe, dead in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wanting as it were the quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit, and feeling ſuch a ſtupified conſcience, as if there were an vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of grace within her: it is like in thoſe men who haue liuing bodies but dead ſoules, vnto whom zeale hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been ſuch a ſtranger, that they neuer knew what the lifting vp of the heart meant. But if we looke vpon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> wee ſhall finde that the ſpirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth within him, and like a floud will not be contained, but his outward acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13734:7"/>ſhall make good his inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hee is truly zealous for Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Now to the intent, that wee may truly conceiue, what this zeale is, that muſt ſhew it ſelfe in the hearts of all them that feare God, I will firſt of all draw forth ſome definition thereof; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards I will ſhew in how many parts it may be ſaid to conſiſt, and thoſe parts ſhall bee proued from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of ſacred Scriptures; and laſt of all I will deſcend vnto vſes, as ſhall bee neceſſarie for our edification.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Definition of zeale.</head>
               <p>Zeale is a feruent and burning af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the hearts of Gods choſen, earneſtly following and louing thoſe things that make for Gods glory; but hating and deteſting ſin, which doth the contrary.</p>
               <p>This definition may be proued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounded vpon the Scripture. For the firſt branch of it, that it is a burning affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within vs for the glory of God, we ſee it proued from the 24. of Luke,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13734:8"/>verſ. 32. <hi>Did not our hearts burne within vs when he expounded the Scriptures,</hi> ſay they, who were going to Emmaus: Chriſt appearing vnto them, but not making himſelfe knowne, doth open vnto them, &amp; expound vnto them the word of God, wherat they reioyce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly. For the other branch, that it is a hating &amp; deteſting of all vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, it is proued in the 139. Pſal. verſ. 21. <hi>Doe not I hate them O Lord that hate thee, and doth not my ſoule earneſtly contend with them that riſe vp against thee?</hi> Thus you ſee the Scriptures doe confirme the definition: now for the parts whereon it may bee ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
               <p>Zeale doth conſiſt on foure parts or points.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 In lamenting of ſinne.</item>
                  <item>2 In puniſhing ſinne.</item>
                  <item>3 In reprouing ſinne.</item>
                  <item>4 In auoiding ſinne.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now you ſhall ſee me returne to the doctrine, and proue, that whoſoeuer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13734:8"/>hath Gods ſpirit, is zealous in all theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the lamenting of ſinne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth here, whoſe <hi>eyes guſh out with water,</hi> wee finde that wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> to doe the like, Chap. 9. verſ. 1. When he ſaw all Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to be out of courſe, the Princes, the Prieſts, and the people: <hi>O</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that my head were a well of water, and my eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſinnes of this people.</hi> Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt alſo confirmeth it in the 19. of Luke, verſ. 41. When he came neere vnto that ſinfull Citie of Hieruſalem, he ſhead teares ouer it, lamenting their wickedneſſe, and the hardnes of their hearts: a moſt pregnant proofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee haue likewiſe in the paſſage betweene <hi>Hazael</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2. King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>p. 8. verſ. 12. When <hi>Hazael</hi> had done his meſſage, and receiued his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, the Prophet lookt, and lookt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him at length fell a weeping: why weepeſt thou (ſaith <hi>Hazael</hi> to <hi>Eliſha) I weepe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to thinke what wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13734:9"/>thou ſhalt commit, and to thinke vpon the euill that thou ſhalt doe vnto Iſrael:</hi> this affection we find in many of Gods children, who many times turne vnto the wall, and lament their owne ſins, wherwith they haue grieued the good ſpirit of God; and when they heare <hi>Rabſaketh</hi> raile againſt God, or <hi>Shimei</hi> curſe <hi>Dauid,</hi> or <hi>Abſolon</hi> rebell againſt his father, or the foole aske who is God, or the ſinner reioyce in that whoſe wages is death, Rom. 6. verſ. 23. They cannot chuſe but lament and powre forth their ſoules vnto God, and no maruell though they ſhew their deuotions and affections vnto their Lord and Maſter in this caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> The firſt reaſon is drawne from the conſideration of the perſon that is offended, and that is God: v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o ſhall plead that mans cauſe that wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinneth againſt God? as old <hi>Ely</hi> ſaith in the 1. Sam. chap. 2. verſ. 25. <hi>If one man ſinne againſt another, the Iudge ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13734:9"/>ſit vpon it, but if a man ſinne againſt God who ſhall plead for him?</hi> the dignitie of the perſon offended aggrauates the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: If a man offer violence to his neighbour, it is the breach of the Law; but if he offer it vnto the Magiſtrate, it is a greater offence; but if it be offered vnto his owne Father, O what a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is this, againſt law, againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, againſt reaſon, againſt religion! O then what is it, when it is offered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? who is it that hath any ſparkles of grace, that can hold him from ſheadding teares in this caſe?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Doth not nature teach vs when our children or our parents die, to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the death of their bodies? and ſhall not grace teach vs to lament the death and ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſoules from the mercies of God, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth on them that liue and die in their ſinnes?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Hath ſinne cauſed thy Chriſt to ſweat both water and blood,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13734:10"/>haue thoſe bitter drops come from him for thee, and comes there no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe from thee in a caſe of ſinne? O God forbid! vnleſſe we be ſtony hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we muſt needs relent: this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Dauid</hi> doth, is but a dutie of Chriſtianity, euen to lament the ſinnes of the people.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Branch of zeale</hi> is for to puniſh ſin, and this euery man ought to doe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in publike or priuate: in publike, that is, if hee haue a lawfull calling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God for that purpoſe; as namely, Magiſtrates and rulers, who carry not the ſword in vaine, Rom. 13. verſe 4. In priuate, that is, to puniſh ſinne in himſelfe, &amp; ſo ſtop the current therof.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, we ſee the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this in <hi>Phineas,</hi> Numb, chap. 25. verſ. 11. <hi>Phineas the ſonne of Eleazar, the ſonne of Aaron hath turned away my wrath, becauſe he was zealous for the Lord;</hi> how? in puniſhing thoſe who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted whoredome in the hoaſt: a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13734:10"/>proofe of like nature wee haue out of the 2. of Kings, chap 10. v. 16. where God commendes the zeale of <hi>Iehu,</hi> in that hee did execute the will of God, which was, that none of <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe ſhould bee left aliue, becauſe hee had wrought ſuch wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord. And to the ſame purpoſe is that commanded in the thirteenth chapter of Deuteronomie, verſ. 6. <hi>If thy brother the ſonne of thy mother, or thy wife that lieth in thy boſome ſhall perſwade thee and entice thee vnto idolatry, then ſhal thy hand be vpon them, and thy eye ſhall not pitie them, for I am the Lord.</hi> Now wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord requireth our zeale in puniſhing ſinne may eaſily appeere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Becauſe hee is a iealous God, and plagueth the ſinner vnto the third and fourth generation: now as the Lord doth this himſelfe, ſo doth he require that thoſe who are as Gods, Pſal. 82.6. ſhall doe the like.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13734:11"/> 2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> He that hath power from God to puniſh ſinne and doth it not, hee doth conclude two things againſt God himſelfe: the one, that God was not wiſe enough in the making of that puniſhment, and therefore man in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing will take vpon him to be wiſer then God.</p>
               <p>The other thing that hee concludes againſt God is, that God is too ſeuere, and therefore man wil ſomtimes ſpare, where God would haue him puniſh; and herein man will take vpon him to be more mercifull then God himſelfe.</p>
               <p>But let the firſt, that wil be wiſer then God, remember <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> who when God will preſerue his <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet this man will take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to giue counſell againſt him; but God confounded <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hitophels</hi> wiſdome, ſo will he do theirs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he that wil be more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull then God, let him remember <hi>Saul,</hi> who for ſparing <hi>Agag,</hi> and the fatlings whom God would haue had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13734:11"/>deſtroyed, had his kingdomerent from him: yea that which was worth ten thouſand kingdomes, God tooke his holy ſpirit from him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> He that ſpareth puniſhing offenders, brings the vengeance vpon his owne head, as <hi>Ely</hi> did, 1 Sam. 3.13. becauſe he would not correct his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, therefore God plagued him.</p>
               <p>Now followeth the priuate puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I mentioned, and that is to bee inflicted vpon our ſelues, not in the courſe of Popiſh penance, by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hairie ſhirts, by whipping our ſelues, or with the Baalites, by cutting or lancing our owne fleſh, not by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing barefoote vpon craggie rockes, or Hermite like, by betaking vs to cels: but by mortifying the fleſh, by brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging downe the body, by that ſorrow which is neuer to be ſorrowed for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cauſeth repentance vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2. cor. 7. verſ. 10. And this is that which the Apoſtle ſpeakes of in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuenth verſe of that chapter: Behold
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13734:12"/>(ſaith he) what zeale this ſorrow hath wrought in you, yea (ſaith hee) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what reuenge it hath wrought in you, that you haue puniſhed ſinne in your ſelues by faſting and prayer, that it had no opportunitie to hold vp a ſcepter within you: and this euery man alſo ought to doe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of Chriſt: <hi>If thine eye offend, plucke it out: &amp; if thy hand offend, cut it off;</hi> that is, auoide thoſe ſins here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that haue come through thine eyes or thy hands, and ſo ſhalt thou be ſaid to obſerue a godly diſcipline, and to keepe (as it were) a houſe of correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thy vnrulie members. And this may ſuffice for the ſecond branch of our zeale, that hee who hath Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit muſt be zealous for Gods glory, in the puniſhing of ſinne publikely vpon others, if hee haue thereunto a calling; and priuately vpon himſelfe, if there be cauſe requiring.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Degree of Zeale</hi> is for the reproofe of ſinne, where the Lord expects not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13734:12"/>onely a weeping eye, and a reſiſting hand, but alſo that there bee an open mouth againſt it: for as in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of a queſtion, our ſilence may inferre a conſent; ſo in the courſe of ſinne, our daintineſſe of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt it, may ſeeme to yeeld ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation vnto it. Therefore God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a zealous affection in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for the reproofe &amp; taking down of them that are growne hardie in a courſe of ſinne. Our God doth this in the 50. Pſalme, verſ. 18. <hi>When thou ſeest a theefe thou art partaker with him, thou ſitteſt alſo and ſpeakeſt againſt thy brother, yea and haſt ſlandred thine owne mothers ſonne:</hi> theſe were fearfull ſinnes: now what will God doe, will hee hold his peace, will he ſtop his eares, and winke with his eyes, as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth many times? no verily: <hi>Theſe things thou haſt done, but I will reproue thee, and ſet before thee the things that thou haſt done.</hi> How ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently alſo doth our Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13734:13"/>this in the 5. chap. to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, the eleuenth verſe: where he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth the children of God to take heed of ſinne, as of a thing that would ſeparate vs from God: <hi>Haue therefore no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darkeneſſe, but rather reproue them.</hi> And it is the charge that <hi>Paul</hi> giues <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2. Tim. chap. 4. verſ. 1. <hi>I charge thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and before Ieſus Chriſt, that ſhall iudge both quicke and dead, that thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, reproue, rebuke, &amp;c.</hi> It was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Church of Epheſus, Reuelat. chap. 2. verſ. 2. in that ſhee could not beare with them which were euill, but muſt needs reproue &amp; reprehend it: and the reaſons are at hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Becauſe heereby thou mayeſt gaine thy brother, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes, Prou. 17.10. <hi>A reproofe entreth more into him that hath vnderſtanding, then an hundred ſtripes into a foole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13734:13"/> 2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> By rebuking of one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may be bettered; which makes the Apoſtle to vrge reproofe of ſinne euen for this cauſe: <hi>Them that ſinne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>rebuke openly, that the reſt may feare.</hi> 1. Tim. chap. 5. verſ. 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> When Chriſt comes in iudgement, he comes to this end, To rebuke the world of ſinne, Ioh. chap. 16. verſ. 8. Therfore his holy ones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his comming muſt bee his mouth as it were, and ſhew that if by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and ſeruants they will not now be reproued, heereafter they muſt bee condemned, when Chriſt comes to reproue the world of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> But it may bee obiected af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner: I ſhall bee counted a buſie-body, and euery one will hate me, what need I runne into theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Indeed <hi>Ieremy</hi> found the truth of this, for he complaineth that euery man hated him, and what had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13734:14"/>hee done to deſerue this? onely told them the truth, reproued them boldly for their ſinnes, Ier. chap. 15. verſ. 10. and <hi>Salomon</hi> foretelleth the ſame, Pro. chap. 9. verſ. 8. <hi>Reproue a ſcorner, and he will hate thee:</hi> yet notwithſtanding thy mouth muſt not be ſealed vp; as for the world, though it hate vs, yet our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that God hath ouercome the world; and therefore to ſatisfie thoſe particulars of being buſie and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling in other mens matters, that the world will ſay, doth not concerne vs: take therfore ſuch rules along with it, as ſhal warrantize reproofe of ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rules for reprouing.</head>
               <p n="1">1. There muſt bee a conſideration of the time: for euery time is not fit for reproofe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There muſt bee a reſpect had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place, for euery place is not fit for the reproofe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There muſt regard be taken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perſon; which is alſo a chiefe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13734:14"/>point both in the matter and manner of reprouing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the time, <hi>Abigael</hi> may be our example, for in 1. Sam. chap. 25. verſe 37. her husband <hi>Naball</hi> being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with drinke, ſhe tooke a golden time, that is, when the wine was out of his head; for to haue told him of it before, had beene to beate the aire, and to haue loſt her labour, hee not being capable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the place, Chriſt may be our example, who in the 16. of Matth. verſ. 23. reprouing of <hi>Peter; Get thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me Satan:</hi> it is when they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues at <hi>Ceſarca Philippi,</hi> none of the malignant ſpirits being by, but his own Diſciples alone with him: and this may bee allowed of amongſt vs for the place that wee chuſe, that when Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are by themſelues, then more liberally may the reproofe be vttered, becauſe Gods enemies will rather reioyce to heare of ſuch infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13734:15"/>amongſt vs, then any way bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the reproofes that are put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the perſon, a double reſpect muſt bee had, firſt in the perſon repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, hee muſt bee called: ſecondly, in the perſon reproued, if he be great. For the firſt, euery man muſt not take vpon him to reproue ſuch, vnleſſe he haue a calling directly leading him therunto: then <hi>Nathan</hi> may ſay plainely euen to <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, if bee ſent, <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> 2. Sam. chap. 12. verſ. 7. For the perſon reproued, care muſt be taken if he be Royall or Noble, there muſt bee reuerence vſed: againe, in the perſon, the perſon we muſt obſerue the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, if hee bee weake and tender, hee muſt bee reſtored with the ſpirit of meekneſſe, leſt hee bee ſwallowed vp, Galath. chap. 6. verſr 1. if hee bee obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, he muſt bee ferreted and vſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> May not the child of God,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13734:15"/>who hath no publike place either in Church or Common wealth, reproue the blaſphemer, or the Sabbath brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, or any other leaud liuer, in reſpect of that which formerly hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes verily, he both may and ought, but yet after ſuch a manner, that the reproofe may ſeeme to be a louing admonition, rather then a bitter repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, becauſe they neuer are ſo wel placed as from a publike calling: and this ſhall ſuffice for the third branch of our zeale, which conſiſteth in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of ſinne.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Branch of zeale</hi> in the deteſtation of ſinne, is to auoid it, and to flie from it.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle inlargeth himſelfe in this point very plainely, in the fifth chapter to the Epheſians; <hi>Haue no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the vnfruitfull works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> and againe in the ſame chapter, ſpeaking of vngodly ones, <hi>Be not compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13734:16"/>of them.</hi> The like ſequeſtration we finde in the 2. Theſſal. chap. 3. verſe 14. <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>obey not, note him, but haue no company with him:</hi> and mark the ſeparation that is required in the eighteenth of the Reuelation, verſ. 4. <hi>Go out of her my people, that you be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her ſinnes, and that you receiue not of her plagues:</hi> now this muſt bee thought vpon, yea and reſolued vpon, leſt we be defiled: as may appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſinne is infectious, like vnto the plague it ſelfe: <hi>Qui tangit pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, coinquinabitur:</hi> hee that toucheth pitch ſhall be defiled; much more hee that conuerſeth with the vngodly, ſhall be polluted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are in danger of our very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and holy profeſſion by vngodly company, and that ſometimes doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate vs from the ſeruice of God: which point is vrged by God againſt <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1. King. chap. 16. verſ. 31. <hi>Was it a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13734:16"/>light thing</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>in Ahab to walk in the ſinnes of Ieroboam the ſonne of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, but hee muſt alſo take to wife Iezabel the daughter of Ethbaal to leade him to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. There are couenants of peace betwixt God and man, and the child of God hath promiſed to forſake the diuell, to renounce the luſts of the fleſh, the pride of the eyes, the vanities of the world: now if thou remember this couenant, thou wilt not looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinne, nor ioyne thy ſelfe to ſinners, zeale wil teach thee, that thou muſt not haue any thing to doe with the ſtoole of wickedneſſe, whereby thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt grieue the good ſpirit of God, whereby thou ſhouldeſt forfeit the grace of God, or defile thy ſoule which is the temple of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sinne though it be ſweet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, yet it is bitter in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, like that booke which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> muſt eate, Reuelat. chap. 10. verſe 9.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13734:17"/>
                  <hi>Sweet in his mouth, but bitter in his bellie:</hi> and like that Image in the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Daniel,</hi> verſ. 35. Whoſe head and beginning was gold, but the feet and latter end thereof was dirt, ſo that this reaſon ſpeaketh home, who would venture his ſoule for a little pleaſure! Sinne is but for a ſeaſon, Heb. chap. 11. verſ. 25. Therefore if thou haue a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heart, thou wilt redeeme that which is paſt, and auoide all euill in the future time which is to come, then ſhalt thou haue leaue to come neare the mercy-ſeate; then ſhalt thou reliſh Chriſt indeed; when once thou begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to loue godlineſſe, it will proue ſuch gaine vnto thee, as thou wilt after chuſe rather to be a dore-keeper in the houſe of God, then to bee a great man in the tents of the vngodly, Pſal. 82.10. And with this I conclude the foure properties of zeale, which ought to bee found in that man who is borne againe, ſuch wil be his loue vnto God,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13734:17"/>and hatred vnto ſinne, that hee will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the people, that hee will puniſh ſinne both in himſelfe and in others, that hee will reproue ſinne without partiality; and finally he will auoide and flie from ſin as from a Serpent.</p>
               <p>Now this peraduenture may paſſe for currant, as being allowed that theſe graces may bee found in ſome men: but it will be ſaid, euery man hath not this grace, no verily, for it is apparent that euery man ſeeketh not for this grace, if they were humble ſutors to the throne of grace, no queſtion but they ſhould preuaile: for <hi>Iacob</hi> is ſo good a wraſtler, that hee lets not goe without a bleſſing; ſo that let the fault bee ours, and not laid vpon our God, for hee is neare vnto them that call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him faithfully: and if any man lacke wiſedome (ſaith Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) let him aske of God, who giueth liberally, and hitteth no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the teeth. Iam. chap. 1. verſ. 5. Wherefore as many as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13734:18"/>to come neare vnto God, although as yet they haue not attained vnto any taſte or comfort from the Lord, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue eare, for I will ſpeake of ſome meanes which are to bee vſed for the encreaſe of our faith, and the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our loue vnto the Almighty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Meanes to beget zeale.</head>
               <p>The firſt is Prayer. The ſecond is the Word. The third is the Sacraments. Theſe are excellent meanes, through which God will anſwere vs, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the new birth of the ſoule vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the firſt, is it not the very ioy of the heart? is it not the good Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan, which wil bind vp our wounds, and heale our ſickneſſe? is it not the cure of affliction? Is any man afflicted, let him pray. I am. chap. 5. verſ. 13. doth not our prayer interpret vnto vs the mercies, of God? doth not <hi>Iacob</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile ouer an Angell by his prayer, Hoſ. chap. 12. verſ. 4. Haue not <hi>Moſes, Ioſuah, Abraham, Elias,</hi> and other of Gods petitioners, what they will (as it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13734:18"/>were) at the hands of God out of their feruent prayers? is there not a heauen vpon earth by the lifting vp of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent hands? is not prayer our greateſt comfort in our greateſt miſery? O if it were not for this, Satan might trample vpon vs, ſinne might ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vs vp, affliction might burie vs aliue, and our corruptions ſo farre preuaile againſt vs, that wee might truely crie with the Apoſtle: O wretched men that wee are, who ſhall deliuer vs!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> It is moſt true, that prayer is very comfortable, &amp; fit to beget zeale, but euery man hath not the gift.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The holy Ghoſt taketh away that obiection, when hee ſaith, that the ſpirit of prayer ſhall helpe our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Rom. chap. 8. verſ. 26. Now then who will not thus aske, that hee may haue, and thus ſeeke, that hee might finde the mercies of God in ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant meaſure?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> But I haue often addreſſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13734:19"/>my ſelfe vnto the Lord in my prayers, and haue ſought the Lord, but had no feeling, and that hath made mee to giue ouer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is in heauenly wiſdome that God doth ſomtimes abate our fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and apprehenſion of his mercy, and that becauſe when wee doe reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtrength, wee ſhall the more cleaue vnto the Lord, and thinke more dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his grace when wee haue it: for no man knowes ſo well what the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of health is, as hee that hath beene ſometime ſicke; and no man hath ſo much cauſe to ſpeake of deliuerance, as he that hath bin in greateſt dangers; for in theſe men there is not onely a view of the action of mercy gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but there is alſo an application, which faſtens God vnto their ſoules for euer after.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is not thy caſe onely to want this feeling at ſome times, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy Chriſt hath in our nature been thus perplexed, <hi>O God my God</hi> (ſaith he)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13734:19"/>
                  <hi>why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, his Church ſo deare vnto him, as that they are the very members of Chriſt Ieſus, they haue this cauſe of complaint ſometimes, Cant. chap. 3. verſ. 1. <hi>In my bed by night I ſought him, but I found him not:</hi> this was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church wanted the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of faith, but that ſometimes ſhee wanted the knowledge of experience; ſhee had not alwaies that feeling as ſometimes ſhee had, and yet who will doubt of the mercy of God towards his Church? Wee ſee that there may bee fire vnder the aſhes, although there be no flame; ſo there is faith at all times in the hearts of Gods children, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometimes they want feeling. Now then if thou wouldeſt haue a zealous heart for Gods glory, vſe this meanes of prayer, and vſe it often, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening and morning, at home, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode; it will (with <hi>Elias</hi>) make thee caſt downe thy looſe mantles of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and profits, when thou ſhalt bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13734:20"/>taken vp into the heauens, as it were, in thy feruent prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> 2. <hi>meanes to beget zeale,</hi> &amp; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it in our hearts, is the bleſſed word of God, that, whereby we are taught, Pſalm. 119. verſ. 33. That which is a lanthorne vnto our feet, and a light vnto our pathes: this ſets forth the mercies of God, and this declares the iudgements of God; in both which alphabets when we grow skilfull, wee ſhall loue God, we ſhall feare God; yea with <hi>Dauid,</hi> wee ſhall hunger after the Lord: and as the Hart brayeth after the riuers of waters, eſpecially when ſhee hath been hunted; ſo will our ſoules long after the Lord our God, Pſal. 42. verſ. 1. If the Scriptures be our ſtudies and our recreations, we ſhall then bee for God indeed; and his word will bee ſweeter to vs then hony or the hony combe: his law will be our delight, &amp; we will ſtudie his ſtatutes both day and night. Now then apply thy ſelfe vnto this, thou that deſireſt that the Sonne
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13734:20"/>of righteouſneſſe ſhould ſhine vpon thy ſoule, and thou ſhalt finde theſe meanes are like the ſteps of <hi>Iacobs</hi> lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, bringing thee by degrees vnto the knowledge of God, and making ſuch loue vnto the Lord in thy prayers, and exerciſes of holy Scripture, that it ſhall appeare thou art both ſanctified and mortified; that thy deſire is to bee with Chriſt, which is beſt of all, Phil. chap. 1. verſ. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> 3. <hi>and laſt meanes,</hi> is the frequent vſe of the bleſſed Sacraments: For the firſt, which is Baptiſme, thou oughteſt to thinke vpon it often, and therein as in a glaſſe to behold thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt ſee therein a double condition: firſt, what thou wert by nature; ſecondly, what thou art by grace; thou ſhalt find that Baptiſme is a lauer of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto thy ſoule, and it wil teach thee an excellent vſe, namely, newneſſe of life; for if any man bee in Chriſt, hee muſt be a new creature, 2. Cor. chap. 5.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13734:21"/>verſ. 17. The other Sacrament, which is the Lords Supper, is as a loue-token betwixt God and thy ſoule: <hi>The King</hi> (ſaith the Spouſe) <hi>hath brought mee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his bed chamber,</hi> Cant. chap. 1. verſe 3. meaning that God had ſhewed her iewels, and rich furniture, whereof ſhe ſhould be partaker. In this Sacrament the Lord doth ſhew himſelfe vnto vs: <hi>As often as you receiue this, do it in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me:</hi> As who ſhould ſay, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what I haue done for you, my body hath been broken, my blood hath beene ſhead for the remiſſion of your ſinnes: now then thinke vpon this, what ioy may it bring vnto you, when as by meanes of faith men may feede vpon Chriſt; how will it ſatisfie doubts, how will it qualifie feare, how will it build vp the ſoule, and beget zeale in ſuch meaſure, as that the man that vſeth theſe meanes ſhall truely ſtand forth in Gods cauſe, with life, with goods, with Chriſtian reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13734:21"/>knowing that hee muſt needs take Gods part, and ioyne with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Gods cauſe, and ſeparate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from Gods enemies, yea grow vp to ſuch a heartie zeale, as that nothing ſhall pleaſe vs, which is diſpleaſing to the Almighty? Then may we truly be called the children of God, when wee feare him, and nothing but him; when we hate euill, for the feare of the Lord is to hate that which is euill, Pro. chap. 8. verſ. 13. When wee know that all our aduantage is in Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eſteeme all but dung in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, Philip. chap. 3, verſ. 8. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we triumph ouer the world, ouer hell, ouer death, ouer our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ouer principalities and powers, and nothing ſhall bee able to ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt Ieſus. And this ſhall ſuffice for the godly meanes, that are to bee vſed for the begetting and encreaſing of zeale within euery one of vs. And now that euery one of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13734:22"/>vs may haue our Gomer full of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, our meaſure of vnderſtanding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this which hath been taught; let vs deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vnto the vſes that flow from this fountaine of doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vſes generally are two.</head>
               <p n="1">1. An inſtruction. 2. A reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>The inſtruction offereth it ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 4. ſorts of people.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Vnto them of <hi>Dauids</hi> ranke, as Kings and Princes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It teacheth <hi>Dauids</hi> Subſtitutes, Magiſtrates and Rulers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It teacheth <hi>Dauids</hi> Mouthes, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It teacheth <hi>Dauids</hi> companions, namely, good Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>All theſe foure are naturally within the inſtruction.</p>
               <p>The reprehenſion reacheth three ſorts of people.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13734:22"/>
                  <item>1. <hi>Nullifidians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Semi-chriſtians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Profeſt wicked ones.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I beginne with the firſt vſe, namely, the inſtruction, which pointeth firſt of all vnto them of <hi>Dauids</hi> ranke, Kings and Princes.</p>
               <p>For as much as <hi>Dauid,</hi> who was both a King, and a Prophet, hath here ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a mornefull preſident; as to open the ſluces, and to powre forth whole riuers of teares, in remembrance of the ſinnes that were daily committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord; it teacheth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vpon earth, euen thoſe that ſit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Thrones, and are the Lords annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſometimes to acquaint their eyes with teares, in token of zealous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, for that Gods law is not kept. They muſt remember that they are nurſing Fathers and Mothers of Gods Iſrael, that they are ſupreame heads and gouernours of the Church; and therefore muſt looke vnto the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13734:23"/>ſoundneſſe of the religion that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that there bee no diſpenſation, neither for <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> nor any other, but as there is but one God, one Faith, one Baptiſme; ſo there may be but one profeſſion in all places, and for all perſons of their dominions.</p>
               <p>It will ſerue alſo to kindle coales of zeale in their royall breaſts, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſuch a loue in them vnto the word of God, that with <hi>Dauid,</hi> in the 15. Pſalme, They will make much of them that feare the Lord; yea when the law is read, with good <hi>Ioſias,</hi> they will melt againe betwixt that ioy and feare, that of right ought to be yeelded vnto it.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, it will teach theſe Heads of the people euen to purge their own houſes: <hi>I will not haue a deceitfull nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly perſon dwell in my houſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> Pſalm. 101. verſ. 7. A worthy pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, and princely preſident for all the world, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they who are as Gods, Pſalm. 82. ſhall thus begin to loue righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13734:23"/>to hate wickedneſſe, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment impieties, who then would not follow ſuch royall examples?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ponitur orbis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe is religious, and ſo tender hearted as to weepe for ſinne, then the laughter of the wicked ſhall bee counted madneſſe, and the mirth of the vngodly ſhall bee turned into heauineſſe; loe, thus ſhall it bee in Iudea, where the King thereof is a man after Gods owne hart: and thus much for that royall ranke.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it teacheth Magiſtrates &amp; Rulers, who are <hi>Dauids</hi> Subſtitutes, how they ſhall diſcharge their duties: <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſo zealous, that when hee comes from God, and findes the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dancing about a Calfe, hee breakes the very Tables of ſtone, out of a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous indignation againſt their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, Exod. chap. 32. verſ. 19.</p>
               <p>Now then if you bee men of God, how can you forbeare your zealous
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13734:24"/>anger againſt ſinne, your Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to behold the vnbridled courſes of ſinne? when you ſhal ſee how deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Cain</hi> is, how prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> is, how careleſſe of the blood (which is ſhead) <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui</hi> are; what ſtrange fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are abroad burning in malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Chriſtian brethren, neuer ſatisfied with reuenge, vntill they haue bathed themſelues in blood; ſuch is the poyſoned nature of our wicked <hi>Catilines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, when wee ſhall ſee the ſmooth ſubtilty of <hi>Gehazi,</hi> who makes obeiſance, and bowes downe to the ground at euery word; who cries, I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, and lye forſooth at euery word.</p>
               <p>When wee ſhall ſee the trechery of <hi>Abſolon</hi> againſt his father; when wee ſhall behold the ſubtilty of <hi>Ziba,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying his maſter; when we ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the infidelity of friends, who with <hi>Iudas,</hi> betray with a kiſſe, and will not ſticke to helpe at a dead lift: hee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13734:24"/>that ſhall obſerue theſe tragicall practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo lately imprinted in the hearts and eares of the people, they may well cry, <hi>O tempora, O mores,</hi> wondring what may bee the end of ſuch curſed begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings!</p>
               <p>Againe, how readie is <hi>Shemei,</hi> and his Romiſh ſpawne, to riſe againſt the Lords annointed; how impudent are they in their ſeducing courſes; &amp; wher will they ſettle, euen as the diuell did, vpon the woman in Paradiſe; then the wife muſt labour the husband; and if ſhe preuaile, then the whole familie is thus poyſoned with Poperie: but if the husband ſhal refuſe, yet the young fry muſt ſucke it (as it were) from the mothers breaſt.</p>
               <p>O if we haue teares, wee ſhall ſhead them at theſe ſights; if we haue zeale, the fire will burſt out, and at the laſt we ſhall ſpeake with our tongues, O Lord God of hoſts, ariſe, and take thy cauſe into thine owne hand. In the meane
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13734:25"/>time, how ought Magiſtrates to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre themſelues, they haue promiſed euery one in their places to do it; nay more, they haue ſworne to execute Iuſtice, which is the greateſt bond, for it is <hi>vinculum Animae,</hi> the very bond of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>If a man bee bound in an hundred thouſand pound, it were a great obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; but when hee is bound in his ſoule by a binding oath, ſealed in the preſence of the bleſſed Trinitie, it is farre beyond the other condition: your authority will hold to puniſh ſin, for it is from God, Rom. 13. v. 1. Thoſe powers that are, they haue their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from God, and who ſo reſiſteth them, reſiſteth the Lord. Now then if you doe not lament it, and puniſh it, and reproue it, and in your owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples auoid it, how can you anſwere it? Looke, I pray you, whether God will take it at your hands, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that iudgement which fell
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13734:25"/>vpon <hi>Ahab</hi> in that caſe of omiſſion. <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>thou haſt let Benha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad goe, when thou ſhouldest haue ſmitten him, thy life ſhall goe for his,</hi> 2. King. chap. 20. verſ. 42. O draw therefore that ſword of Iuſtice, let it not ruſt in the ſcabbard; do not rattle the poore that offend, and afterwards ariſe vp vnto the rich, and bend, when they are in the ſame ſinne: No, remember thou muſt not fauour the perſon of the poore, nor reſpect the perſon of the rich; but remember who is offended, God; and remember who will not be pacified, vntil <hi>Ionas</hi> be flung ouer bord. Now therfore dallie not with him, leſt our great ſhip, I meane the whole land; and our beſt wares, I meane the word of God; and our deareſt liues, with all the reſt of the tackle ſhould proue in danger, euen for the ouer much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuencie and pitie ſhewed vnto them, who remaine incorrigible, inconuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, and may hereafter proue as into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13734:26"/>Be affected therefore with this you Magiſtrates, &amp; Rulers, ſhew your zeale for Gods glory, and you your ſelues thus diſcharging your duty, ſhall reape of the Lords mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third inſtruction is to teach them, that ſhould teach others, whom I cal <hi>Dauids</hi> Mouthes, euen godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: If they ſhould not mourne for the ſinnes of the people, it were very ſtrange; if they ſhould not reproue ſinne, it were much to be wondred at; and if they themſelues ſhould not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide ſinne, it were as much to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented? Theſe are the lights of the world, and therefore muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the workes of darkeneſſe; theſe are the Lords trumpetters, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt needs ſound forth his praiſe: If theſe men ſhould hold their eyes from weeping, their mouthes from ſpeaking, their hearts from throbbing and groning within them, when God is diſhonoured, the very ſtones of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13734:26"/>ſtreet might riſe vp in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. But how wofull is the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, that may bee taken vp for want of lamentation by theſe men? whoſe eyes ſhould guſh out with teares, whoſe mouthes ſhould reproue ſinne both in ſeaſon, &amp; out of ſeaſon, 2. Tim. chap. 4. verſ. 2. and yet there is that <hi>altum ſilentium,</hi> as it may be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red where the Seers are, and where the ſpeakers are, that ſhould open their mouthes againſt theſe ſinnes. There are diuers diſeaſes crept in amongſt vs, which turne to a kind of pippe, in the mouthes of many of vs; ſome of vs haue gags in our mouthes, and thoſe cannot pronounce one word; they may be faire readers, but I am ſure they are no ſpeakers in Gods Parliament. houſe heere on earth, which is his Church: yet bleſſed be God, this euill beginneth to bee taken away in many places, and moſt Churches better fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of late, then euer they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13734:27"/>otherſome of vs haue Cankers in our mouthes, and they haue ſore throtes, through a kinde of deſuetude and ceſſation of ſpeaking; this diſeaſe beginneth commonly on one ſide of the mouth, but in time turneth about vnto the other ſide; there are very <hi>non reſidentes,</hi> that can finde out the cauſe of this, for it is ſo ſore a Canker, that they of all men are loth to touch it; yet true it is, that this Canker, or Cancer, deuoureth more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would ſerue two or three, and ſo ceaſeth not to feed as long as any matter may be applied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: this hinders their pronuntiation, and makes them paſſe ouer a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinnes in their brethren, leſt their owne ſhould come in queſtion. This euill were the leſſe dangerous, if the worthies of our Church, who both in reſpect of their dignities, and eminent gifts might haue the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus: who without ſome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meanes cannot maintaine their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13734:27"/>ſtates, nor degrees: but when plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities ſhall bee conferred vpon them, who are not able to ſtand in the gap, betwixt God and the people; when our dumb Miniſters, who are not able to watch ouer ſoules, nor able to make laments, or to ſhead moaning teares for the people; when theſe ſhall dip their feet in oyle, and thus eate vp the fat of the earth; it is no ſmall ſinne in themſelues, nor no little grieuance to others: but moſt of the fault is in <hi>Gehazi;</hi> for <hi>Eliſha</hi> did not conſent that <hi>Gehazi</hi> ſhould runne for his change of raiment, and two talents of ſiluer for the young men, 2. King. chap. 5. but <hi>Gehazi</hi> gets it by a lie, and forged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: &amp; ſo no queſtion there are cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the like nature taken, to make ſome men capable of pluralities, who are more fit to keepe ſheepe, then to feede the flocke. Let vs therefore take it to heart, that deſire to be faithfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſers of the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13734:28"/>Let vs be grieued to heare, and ſee wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grieue the good ſpirit of God; let vs of all men bee free from it our ſelues, and ſo we ſhall bee the fitter to reproue others. But yet there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complaint to be made againſt our ſelues, who ought to bee <hi>Dauids</hi> Mouthes: for as the firſt ſort haue gags in their mouthes, and ſo cannot ſpeak: &amp; a ſecond ſort haue Cankers in their mouthes, and will not ſpeake: ſo there is a third ſort, who haue ſugar pellets in their mouthes, and ſpeake ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they will diſcouer themſelues ſo plainely, as that the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſhall beare witneſſe they can diſſemble. Their common place is <hi>placentia,</hi> wherein they ſo excell, that <hi>Apelles</hi> himſelf could neuer paint more liuely then they. Alas, my brethren, is this the way to gaine ſoules? is this the way to bring men out of darknes, and ſhadowes of death? no ſurely, this will nurſe them in ſinne, and hold a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13734:28"/>candle to their tranſgreſſion; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if euer wee will doe good in the Church of God, let vs take example from <hi>Dauid,</hi> by weeping for the ſinnes of the people, &amp; by reprouing of their ſinnes, without reſpect of perſons; leſt it be ſaid that with <hi>Ianus</hi> we haue two faces, and can to day frowne vpon ſin, and to morrow can laugh at the ſame: and this ſhall ſuffice for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who are appointed by God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct others.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who in the vſe of this doctrine are inſtructed, are thoſe whom I called <hi>Dauids</hi> companions, namely, good Chriſtians: <hi>I am a companion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vnto all them that feare God.</hi> They are taught alſo a dutie, and that is, inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be affected with griefe, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God is diſhonoured: let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member God is their Father; will a ſonne ſtand by and here his earthly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther railed vpon, and will hee hold his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13734:29"/>peace? and can the child of God heare and ſee his heauenly Father blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, his Redeemer crucified againe, the bleſſed and ſanctifying Spirit grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and doth not all this trouble him? Looke vpon <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalm. 120. verſ. 5. <hi>Woe is me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I am conſtrained to dwell in Meſech, and to haue my habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the tents of Kedar.</hi> Iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> was grieued with the ſinnes of Sodome, and ſo muſt iuſt men bee touched, and pricked in their hearts for to ſee God diſhonoured, which will take away all theſe euaſions and ſlips that many vſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Euery man ſhall anſwere for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die; yet for all this remember, God looketh to haue thy heart well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and thy tongue zealouſly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſpeake in the Lords cauſe, leſt thy ſilence may couer conſent, &amp; thou ſeeme aſhamed of thy maſters cauſe; whereof let euery man take heed, leſt Chriſt bee aſhamed of him in his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13734:29"/>kingdome: and ſo I conclude the vſes that belong to the Inſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. The ſecond generall vſe that was drawne from the former doctrine, I called Reprehenſion; and it tooke hold eſpecially of three ſorts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Of Nullifidians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Of Semi-chriſtians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Of Profest wicked ones.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt of theſe are our godleſſe Atheiſts, theſe men muſt needs bee far from God, when they will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no God at all: <hi>Theſe men</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>cannot pleaſe God,</hi> Hebr. 11. neither are they diſpleaſed at any thing that ſhall be diſpleaſing to his Maieſty. This vſe therefore of reprehenſion firſt ceazeth vpon them: The very oxe and Aſſe know their maſter, and their maſters cribbe, Eſa. 1. But theſe men know not God. The heauens declare his glory, and the firmament ſetteth forth his handie work; but theſe earth-wormes wil declare nothing, but their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13734:30"/>reſeruation vnto the day of vengeance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſort iuſtly to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued from this doctrine, are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different men, whom I call <hi>Semi-chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> Theſe men with <hi>Agrippa,</hi> Act. 26. are almoſt perſwaded to bee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and a little thing will diſſwade them to the contrary. Theſe men haue no teares in their eyes for God, and though they ſhould ſtand by, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Chriſt vpon the Croſſe, with all the deſpitefull vſage they vſed againſt him, yet theſe men would both hold their tongues, their eies, &amp; their hands, and bee ſo farre from taking part with Ieſus, that with <hi>Peter</hi> in his weakeneſſe they would follow him a farre off. Matth. 26. Theſe men out of a luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme obſeruation, will venture the ſpewing out of Gods mouth, Reuel. chap. 3. Lord, how hot and earneſt theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil be in a reuenging courſe, againſt the man that ſhal impaire their credit? but they can ſtand by whileſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13734:30"/>their Chriſt is raild vpon, whiles the blaſphemer doth diue into his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wounds, and it neuer troubles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; this ſhewes their loue is little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to God; for where the Lord hath gained the heart, there hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the heart, there the eyes ſhead riuers of teares; there the tongue pleades, and the groanes of greefe, and ſorrowfull ſighs are as often vttered, as God is offended: Know then, thou halfe-Chriſtian, that thou art but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the child of God, and ſhalt neuer attaine vnto it altogether, vntill thou haue <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, and zealous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that is, to bee grieued in a caſe of ſinne, becauſe it is done againſt the Maieſty of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third perſon reprehended, is the profeſſed and habituated ſinner, he that ſold himſelfe to commit ſinne, hee that with <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> makes Iſrael to ſinne; O drawes others to hell, and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops himſelfe thither, leſt he ſhould not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13734:31"/>haue time enough to runne to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Doe theſe men take it to heart when God is offended? no verily, but they reioyce, and make it the very ioy of their hearts, and the ſole delight of their eyes, when they can draw others to be partakers of vngodlineſſe. Thus <hi>Ieroboam</hi> makes Iſrael ſinne, and claps his hands at the fall of the righteous; it is their ſport: and as the Philiſtims did make themſelues merry with <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> vntill the houſe was pluckt ouer their eares; ſo they, who with <hi>Ahab,</hi> haue ſold themſelues to commit ſinne, will neuer giue ouer their helliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, vntill God pay them their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with his heauie vengeance. Theſe are they that the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, in the firſt chapter to the Romans, the one and thirtieth verſe: which men do not onely commit things worthie of death, but alſo fauour, and delight in them that doe the like. If I ſhould bee required to amplifie this part of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13734:31"/>reprehenſion with ſome inſtance: Is it not ſeene, my brethren, that there are thoſe who ſpend their time, and their eſtate in this kind? are not thoſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places? nay, in moſt places, that lay plots to diſcouer their brothers naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: O theſe are curſed <hi>Chams!</hi> that will make them naked, and then diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their nakedneſſe: theſe men are ſtrong to drinke, but woe vnto them, Eſa. chap. 5. verſ. 22. O you <hi>Ieremies</hi> of this land, weepe for this ſinne: O you <hi>Dauids,</hi> men after Gods owne heart, ſhead riuers of teares, to ſee how theſe vngodly ones will run vp and downe, to ouertake a weake braine, &amp; at length will ſo inure them to that ſinne, that they will alſo hunt after wickedneſſe in the ſame kinde. Theſe damnable imps doe count it a greate glory, to make their poore brethren in ſuch a ſinfull taking, as that with drunkennes they ſtrip them out of their reaſon, wit, memory, ſenſe, and feeling; and when
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13734:32"/>a man is thus transformed into a beaſt, by their wickednes, then this is their glory. But ſhall I ſhew them what will bee the end of this glory, the Prophet tels them, Habak. 2.15. <hi>Woe vnto him that giueth his neighbour drinke, thou ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thine heate, and makeſt him drunken alſo, that thou mayeſt ſee their priuities, but the cup of the Lords right hand ſhall bee powred vpon thee, and ſhamefull ſpewing ſhall be for thy glory:</hi> Loe what thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is, nothing but ignominie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch; like vnto the alteration that the daughters of Iuda finde, Eſa. 3. Their beauty is turned to baldneſſe; their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes to ſtenches; their muſicke, and blithe-full melodie, to anguiſh, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame miſery. Looke then vpon your portions, you vngodly ones, although you may ſing to the Violl and harpe for a time, yet there will bee a blacke and gloomie day; but as for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, who haue ſhead teares, great ſhall their ioy bee, for they haue their bleſſing from Chriſts owne mouth,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13734:32"/>Mat. 5. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourne now, they ſhall reioyce hereafter:</hi> and, <hi>they that ſow in teares, ſhall reape in ioy.</hi> O bleſſed harueſt, &amp; glorious triumph! O happy teares, to gaine ſuch immortall ioyes! O triumphant ſtate and condition for the elect, who haue bin ſo accuſtomed to a courſe of mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as that they haue bin true mourners indeed! They ſhal hereafter be clothed in white, they ſhall wait vpon the Lamb, they ſhal ſee God, they ſhall inherit with Chriſt, they haue ſuffered with him, they ſhall raign with him. Finally, they ſhal haue fellowſhip with God, &amp; his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: loe thus ſhall the men be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that honour God, &amp; thus ſhall it be vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who are heires of ſaluation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in Ieſus Chriſt: Vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Father, and the moſt bleſſed Spirit, one Eternall, immortall, inuiſible, and God only wiſe, be aſcribed all honour, praiſe, might, maieſty. glory, &amp; domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
